how can we distinguish when a trait is
the product of adaptive evolution versus
drift so I need to tell you a little
history first back in I think 1979 the
very famous paleontologists Stephen Jay
Gould and his less famous very important
geneticists but less publicly famous
geneticist friend Richard Lewin ttan
published a very famous paper about the
field of evolutionary biology paper is
called the spandrels of San Marcos and
it is about an architectural analogy for
things that are seen in creatures and it
made a very forceful argument paper
argued that evolutionary biologists were
getting carried away with explanations
that were adaptive and the point was
that in this Cathedral there were these
things called spandrels and the
spandrels had these very beautiful
pictures in them that made it seem like
the spandrels had been created to house
these pictures I think there's one
famous rotunda that has four pillars
underneath this dome and each of the
pillars has a triangular spandrel that
it creates and the four spandrels have
been filled in with maybe they're Saints
that represent different rivers or
something like that it all looks like
the spandrels are there for this very
important purpose Gould and Lou Anton's
argument was of the spandrels are
actually an architectural accident of
what happens when you put a dome on top
of pillars now this is not inherently
true but even if we grant that part of
the puzzle their argument had a kind of
disastrous effect on evolutionary
biology it had a degree of truth in it
there was a tendency amongst
evolutionists to gravitate in the
direction of
explanations for traits of creatures
that seemed right in spite of the fact
that there wasn't sufficient evidence to
know that these explanations were right
but what they said was look that
adaptations arise because you have
genetic variation and because selection
favors certain variants over others so
if you're gonna claim that something is
an adaptation you should demonstrate
that the state that you wish to claim is
adaptive is actually superior to the
alternative states this all seems very
reasonable and conservative it's
actually insane right when we get to a
creature very frequently the race is
over
whatever selective advantage the trait
had is gone because all of the creatures
have it so you have what's called
fixation where every creature has the
trait in question and there's nothing to
measure so that's one problem I mean
that which remains becomes the
definition of the creature anyway it
does but I mean look just take a stupid
example your heart has four chambers
it's quite clear that a four chambered
heart has advantages in terms of
efficiency because it isolates the
oxygenated blood from that that's been
depleted there's no doubt that that's
why it evolved even if there were humans
that occasionally had that variance and
even if you had the budget to find the
genes responsible for the difference
you're talking about an immense
investment in research to prove
something that's utterly obvious which
is that keeping the oxygenated blood
separate from the depleted blood has
efficiency advantages so when I got to
graduate school I became frustrated by
the fact that Gould and Lou Anton's
argument was still live and that many of
the people I was interacting with took
it as an important set of criteria
whereas other people I dealt with
understood that they needed to simply
ignore it
this was not satisfying to me I wanted
to come up with a logically robust way
to neutralize the part of that argument
that wasn't real and so I did when I
came up with was a test and the test has
four parts and it allows you to restore
the burden of proof to the way it should
logically be so Luton and Gould had
reversed the burden of proof and
basically set a very high bar for
claiming of the traits that an organism
has are the product of adaptive
evolution my point was actually almost
every trait you could name of a creature
is the product of adaptive evolution and
so it shouldn't have a high bar
logically speaking it shouldn't
evolution is formally defined as changes
in gene frequency within a population
over time that process evolution can be
caused by various things it can be
caused by creatures migrating into a
landscape leaving a landscape dying or
it can be caused by the fact that within
that landscape selection of favors
certainly genetic variance over others
so only that last one creates adaptive
evolution the only process that creates
anything meaningful is adaptive
evolution drift can certainly change
gene frequencies but it can't create a
wing or an eye or almost anything you
could name and by meaningful you mean
something that persists and then games
definitive of this organism no I mean
something you could name there are
examples of things you could name that
don't have any adaptive meaning but you
actually have to work a little bit to
find them and I'll let me come to some
example so that you can see what I mean
the test that I came up with involved
four criteria if all four criteria are
met you are logically justified in
assuming that adaptive evolution is the
explanation unless
countervailing evidence arises so the
four characteristics are complexity
complexity is only created at high
degrees by adaptive evolution in the non
adaptive part of the universe there is
nothing highly complex there are some
curious things there are some structured
things but complexity is different the
second criterion is that the trait in
question has to have a cost that cost
can be in terms of materials or it could
be a cost in terms of risk that the
organism takes but some cost that the
organism would be better off not paying
if it weren't of some value the third
characteristic is that there has to be
variation in the amount of cost that is
spent so that creatures that spend less
would have a competitive advantage over
creatures that spend more and the fourth
is persistence over evolutionary time if
a trait is complex that suggests
adaptive evolution if it has a cost and
that cost varies and yet creatures that
pay the cost are not being out competed
by creatures that save on the cost over
evolutionary time that suggests of the
trait in whatever way is paying for
itself that is the core piece of logic
that allows us to presume that some
trait is the consequence of adaptive
evolution
so if we look at the plant and we
discover that the green color of the
grass is the result of a pigment
molecule
well the pigment molecule is complex as
is the metabolic process that creates it
the pigment molecule is costly it's made
out of materials that the grass could
use for something else if it wanted to
it is variable the degree to which a
plant invests in chlorophyll varies some
produce more per unit of volume of leaf
some produce less and it persists over
evolutionary time plants continue to be
green now we can say that we can presume
that that molecule and therefore the
green color of the plants is the result
of adaptive evolution the trick is we
cannot say based on that evidence what
the green color is for we can just say
what process created it now it happens
that in the case of the color of plants
we know what the molecule does molecule
absorbs light energy and turns it into
chemical energy which the plant can
store and deploy for different things
but there lots of cases in which a trait
of an organism passes the test but we
don't know what it's for
for example there's a an extinct clade
of creatures called palooka soars
amongst them Dimetrodon Dimetrodon and
the other Palicki soars are very
conspicuous these are creatures that
lived on the earth with the dinosaurs
they were not dinosaurs but they lived
at the same time and they had these
marvelous sails on their backs these big
sails that had bones sticking up to hold
them open like a giant wing we don't
know whether the sails on the back of
these animals collected sunlight to warm
their blood to give them an advantage so
that they didn't have to warm up their
dense bodies in the sunlight or if they
deterred predators we can't say for sure
now it is possible using fossil evidence
to answer a question right
but we should not confuse the question
of what is the sale on the back of the
palooka sore for with the question of is
it and adaptation my point would be you
have to separate those two questions
it is absolutely obvious that the sale
on the back of the palooka store is an
adaptation there's no way that that sale
would have ended up on so many species
that lasted over so many generations if
it was a waste
it had to be paying for itself in what
way was it paying for itself is a
separate question a more interesting
question and a more difficult question
so I don't know if we will ever know the
answer for sure but the mistake that Lou
Anton and Gould caused us to make was to
confuse these two questions where if we
couldn't explain what the sale was for
we had no justification for claiming it
was for anything and that's a logical
fallacy so let's take an example that
fails the test if we look at the
coloration of naked mole-rats naked
mole-rats live almost their entire lives
underground
they only very occasionally one
individual will leave one burrow run
across the African plains and dive into
another burrow so they almost never end
up in the light they're in the dark for
their whole lives
they are almost hairless and they are
some kind of gray color now if that grey
color is the result of a pigment if
there's a molecule that makes them gray
well then it passes the adaptive test on
the other hand if there's no molecule
that makes them gray if they are gray
because being some color doesn't pay if
you're in the dark and so evolution has
economized
on making a pigment and it's just
allowed them to be whatever car you are
if you've got enough pigment then well
there's no cost to being the color they
are so we can't say that that color is
adaptive now surely the loss of the
color is adaptive and it's not
incidental that a creature that lives
where there's no light happens to be one
that is abandoned making pigments but
from the point of view of saying that
particular color of naked mole-rats
is adaptive
nope I don't think we have that evidence
so my argument is not that this test
shows us something amazing it doesn't it
shows us something that ought to be
obvious to us something that was
completely obvious to Darwin
incidentally that when a creature spends
on something okay that it does so for a
reason and if it didn't do so for a
reason it would economize and there
therefore it would reallocate whatever
materials and energy it was spending on
something else so Darwin was sent a
specimen and a walk in from Madagascar I
believe he was sent it by Bateman and it
was a very spectacular specimen in the
sense that this work 'add had a very
long nectar tube like a foot long so the
nectar was formed at the bottom of this
very long tube that hangs off of this
flower and Darwin reasoned there must be
a moth out there with a tongue long
enough to get to the bottom of this
thing otherwise why would this plant
make this amazing structure it makes no
sense for a plant to make a nectary that
can't be accessed by a pollinator and he
did not live to see the answer but in
fact a moth Xanthippe an Morgana was
discovered that in fact has this
incredibly long tongue and does indeed
pollinate this particular orchid so my
point is you know Darwin was an amazing
gene is one of the absolute grades but
this amazing genius was saying something
perfectly straightforward that it would
not make sense if his hypothesis of
natural selection was correct it not
makes sense for a plant to invest in a
nectary that could not be accessed by
any pollinator they would not do
anything useful for the plant therefore
in light of the fact that he was looking
at this flower there had to be a
pollinator to match that's obviously
correct my four-part test of adaptation
is a revival of that kind of thinking
and the whole idea is that it should
free us from the absurd obstacles to
claiming that something is an adaptation
which almost every trait of almost every
creature that you could name is and the
reason to free us is not that it is so
marvelous to point to all these
structures and say they're the product
of adaptive evolution of course they are
adaptive evolution is the only process
that creates high degrees of complexity
in the first place so versus each oh
yeah so virtually everything you should
you could name about creatures oughta
pass this test the purpose of it though
is for us to be able to move on to the
interesting question the interesting
question is the ones that preoccupy me
and all of my evolutionarily oriented
friends are the questions about why what
is the value of this thing to the
creature and sometimes it's perfectly
obvious as in the case of a chlorophyll
molecule that's capturing sunlight and
sometimes it's complex enough to stifle
us for decades nobody has yet delivered
a compelling explanation for why
peacocks or peacock spiders or our Birds
go through the incredible expense of
males demonstrating to female something
that is of no particular value in the
raising of offspring why do females
require this of males so we've talked
about this in a previous video but the
basic point is look that set of
behaviors that we call lekking passes
the adaptive test does that say what
it's for no that's still an interesting
question
religion passes the adaptive test it's
complex it's expensive there's a
variance and how much creature spend on
it and it lasts over evolutionary time
gives the lens an advantage to those
that write but the point is we want to
be liberated from the question of is it
adaptive in order to pursue the question
how could that possibly be adaptive
why would believing in Heaven or Hell or
deities who are allowable to respond to
your prayers why would that be good for
you
right it wouldn't be better for you to
think hey there's nobody out there I
better look out for myself
first order it sort of seems like that
would be the way to go apparently not
apparently people believe in that
somebody gives a damn about them and is
watching over them and that if they
happen to end up in some circumstance
they can't get themselves out of and
they've kept their account clean with
you know the the sky god that they will
end up in some great place forever
somehow that belief appears to be
valuable well that's a worthy thing to
study how could it be so anyway my point
is being freed from the question of
whether or not things are adaptive
leaves us open to study in what way
things that are obviously adaptive are
beneficial and that's where the
interesting stuff in evolutionary
biology happens
you